<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A perfect and easie treatise of the vse of the cœlestiall globe written aswell for an introduction of such as bee yet vnskilfull in the studie of astronomie: as the practise of our countriemen, which bee exercised in the art of nauigaiton. Compiled by Charles Turnbull: and set out with as much plainnes as the author could: to the end it might of euery man be vnderstood.</title>
            <author>Turnbull, Charles.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1585</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14030</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24337</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118700</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853907</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853907</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19308</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14030)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19308)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 552:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A perfect and easie treatise of the vse of the cœlestiall globe written aswell for an introduction of such as bee yet vnskilfull in the studie of astronomie: as the practise of our countriemen, which bee exercised in the art of nauigaiton. Compiled by Charles Turnbull: and set out with as much plainnes as the author could: to the end it might of euery man be vnderstood.</title>
                  <author>Turnbull, Charles.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[by G. Robinson] for Symon Waterson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1585]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name and publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The vse of the globe.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Celestial globes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19308:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19308:1"/>
            <p>A perfect and eaſie <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the vſe of the coelestiall</hi> Globe: written aſ well for an <hi>Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of ſuch as bee yet vnskilfull in</hi> the ſtudie of Aſtronomie: as the practiſe of our Countriemen, which bee exerciſed in the Art of Nauiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Compiled by <hi>Charles Turnbull:</hi> And ſet out with as much plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes as the Author could: to the end it might of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood.</p>
            <bibl>Pſalm. xix.</bibl>
            <q>The heauens declare the glorie of God, and the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament ſheweth the worke of his handes. Day vnto day vttereth the ſame, and night vnto night teacheth knowledge.</q>
            <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at London for</hi> Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Waterſon.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19308:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19308:2"/>
            <head>INSIGNISSIMO VIRO, AC OMNI VIR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum genere clariſsimo Magiſtro Henrico Nocllo, Carolus Turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bullus ſalutem ac foelicita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem perpetuam com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precatur.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>VM antiquiſſimorum ſcripto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſingularem industriam in ſtudijs Mathematicis iam an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſeriùs, accuratiúſque cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerim: &amp; recentium quorun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam deprauatam lectionem ſumma cura, ſummáque diligentia viderim &amp; obſeruaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim: ne infestus error damnum inferret gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius: curaui (vir inſigniſſime) ea faciliùs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicare, quae ſi fideliter diſcantur, omnis er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roris tollent difficultatem. Eorum verò te pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronum eſſe volui, vt meo exemplo ad eadem vota multos inuitem, tanquam indicem te, in florentiſſimo hoc regno non ſolùm tanti nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tij virum celeberrimum: ſed omnium regia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum virtutum laudúmque patronum. Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que
<pb facs="tcp:19308:3"/> minuſculam opus hoc A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, qualecunque ſit, (quod ſcio quam ſit indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnum) tibi dedico: vt qui imposterum non ſolum obſeruationes astronomicas elaboratas magis, minúſque vſitatas: (ſiue ſint theorica ſiue horalogica) ſed opticas quoque &amp; qua ſunt geometriae communis praecepta, (vt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus poſtulat) ſis receptarus. Quibus vt es ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus nobiliſſimi: ita mirificè quoque delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris. Vnum hoc interim precibus etiam at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que etiam obſecrans: vt qua huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate erga me ſemper vſus es. (cum maxime poſſis:) eadem iam indies confirmata magis (libertiſſime quoque velis patroci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nari.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19308:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>En which are more deſirous of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique Fame and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now ne, then ſtudious of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon profit: with great curioſitie ſet a glaſſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch things, as being diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, would ſhew diſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred &amp; miſhapen. (As for my ſelfe I ſeeke no higher digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, then to be reported to ſet forth a trueth: and therefore without any wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted cloquence, I make bold to offer the vſe of the Globe, to the exquiſite vewe of your curious eyes: (though farre in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour as I ſuſpect to ſome mens expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation) to the end ſuch groſſe enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties might bee amended, as often times in diuers haue bene diſcouered. Who for want of right conceat of things by them attempted: haue in the ayer built ſuch fortreſſes, as haue without aſſalts woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their louing enemies. But happely
<pb facs="tcp:19308:4"/> ſuch men wil now retire, and arme them ſelues better againſt the next aſſault, leſt they be like to the dogs in the capitall of <hi>Rome:</hi> which were placed to the end, that if by night ſpoylers ſhould ariue, they might ſound a warning. For, true it is, that by night theſe barke out falſe Allaromes at their enimies: but if by day, they barke likewiſe at friends: I hope ye wil iudge them worthy to haue their legs broken. which things I leaue to your gentle interpretation. Nothing miſdoubting, but if in this tract either anything bee eſcaped contrarie to my will: or omitted not ſatiſfying your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation: ye wil aequally ſuffer the ſame. For if ye receaue the fruites of my labor and care of your commoditie, I require no more. Wherefore my trauaile I bequeath to your diſcreet conſideration, and your ſelues to the protection of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="definitions">
            <pb facs="tcp:19308:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>DEFINITIONS to be praemiſed</hi> neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>of the Globe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Sphaere or Globe, is a perfect round &amp; ſollide bodie, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnder one ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficies or face; in whoſe middle is a point, from which point all lines that are drawne to the ſuperficies and face of the ſame: are aequall the one to the other.</p>
            <p>The Center of the Sphaere, is the middle point of the ſame.</p>
            <p>The Axe of the Sphaere, is a
<pb facs="tcp:19308:5"/> right line paſſing from one ſide of the ſame, (by his Center) to the contrary ſide, about which line the Sphaere is caried: but the line it ſelf ſtandeth ſtill.</p>
            <p>The Poles of the Sphere, be the endes of his Axe.</p>
            <p>The Pole of any Circle, is a point without the compaſſe of the ſame: (and yet is aequally distant from all points, of the circuit or borders of the Circle whoſe Pole it is:) &amp; from which the ſame Circle is drawne.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:19308:5"/>
               <head>OF THE NAME of the Sphaere, and his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and ſundrie kindes of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſions: together with the motion of ech one in his kinde.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE NAME OF</hi> the <hi>Sphaere,</hi> is taken either generally or par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticularly. Generally, and ſo it is ſaid to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine all perfect round bodies, whether they be ſollide or not: whether contained vnder one onely <hi>Superficies</hi> or moe. And ſo may euery Orbe be called a <hi>Sphaere.</hi> But if wee take the worde <hi>Sphaera,</hi> in his particular and proper ſignification: then nothing is a <hi>Sphaere:</hi> but a perfect round bodie being ſollide, contained vnder one, &amp;c. as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer definition declared. This <hi>Sphaere</hi> is
<pb facs="tcp:19308:6"/> diuided either according to his ſubſtaunce: or according to certaine properties and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections which he is capable of.</p>
               <p>According to his ſubſtance he is diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into two parts: the one <hi>Elementall,</hi> the other <hi>Aethercall.</hi> The <hi>Elementall,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth the fower Elements, Fire, Ayre, Water and Earth: and is ſubiect to altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, by reaſon of their effectual working. The <hi>Aethercall,</hi> compaſſeth in round, the <hi>Elementall</hi> part, in his hollowneſſe, and is lightſome by nature, and vnchaungeable: and containeth ten <hi>Sphaeres.</hi> The firſt and higheſt from the earth, being called the firſt moueable, containeth in his hollowneſſe al the other: and by his natural motion is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued directly from the Eaſt to the Weſt, and ſo to Eaſt againe, in the ſpace of 24. ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers continually, and carieth about with him by violence, al the other <hi>Sphaeres.</hi> The next vnder this is the ninth <hi>Sphaere,</hi> called the Chriſtall heauen, and by his naturall motion is caried from Weſt toward Eaſt, but very ſlowly, in many yeares paſſing but one degree: and this motion hath cauſed the Starres to alter their Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gitudes. The third <hi>Sphaere</hi> is the Firmament or <hi>Sphaere</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19308:6"/> of the fixed Starres: whoſe motion by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is vpon two little Circles: the one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſcribed about the head of <hi>Aries,</hi> and the other of <hi>Libra:</hi> which motion is called the motion of <hi>Trepidation.</hi> The other ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>Sphaeres</hi> be of the ſeauen Planets: the higheſt of <hi>Saturne,</hi> which moueth by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from Weſt toward Eaſt, and that in 30. yeares one perfect reuolution. The next of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> moouing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Weſt to Eaſt by nature, and that in twelue yeares. The other of <hi>Mars,</hi> making his reuolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from Weſt toward Eaſt in two yeares. Vnder <hi>Mars</hi> is the Sunne, moouing by nature from Weſt toward Eaſt, making one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect reuolution in 365. daies and 6. howers almoſt. Vnder the Sunne is <hi>Venus,</hi> and then <hi>Mercurie,</hi> moouing from Weſt to Eaſt about the ſame time as the Sunne. The laſt is the Moone, making one perfect reuolution from Weſt toward Eaſt in 27. daies. 7. howers. 43′. 7″. yet all theſe are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by violence of the firſt moueable from Eaſt to Weſt, as is before ſaide.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:19308:7"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>OF THE CIR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the Sphaere of Heauen, and of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and how they be made.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Stronomers to the end they might ſhewe the motions of Heauen, and the ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge and wonderful concluſions of the <hi>Coeleſtiall</hi> bodies: haue ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined certaine Circles in the bodie of the firſt <hi>Sphaere</hi> or firſt mooueable, and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally ten: whereof ſome be greater Circles of the <hi>Sphaere,</hi> ſo called becauſe the Center of theſe Circles is alſo the Center of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: &amp; euery ſuch Circle diuideth the whole <hi>Sphaere</hi> into two <hi>aequall</hi> parts. Of this ſort be ſixe: the <hi>Aequinoctiall, Zodiack, Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon, Meridian,</hi> and two <hi>Colures.</hi> Some bee leſſer Circles of the <hi>Sphaere</hi> ſo called, becauſe they haue not the Center of the world for their Center, neither diuide the whole <hi>Sphaere aequally.</hi> Of this kinde be fower, the Tropicke of <hi>Cancer,</hi> the Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picke of <hi>Capricorne,</hi> the Articke and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarticke.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19308:7"/>
               <p> The <hi>Aequinoctiall,</hi> called the <hi>aequator</hi> or girdle of Heauen, is a great Circle of the <hi>Sphaere,</hi> diuiding the <hi>Sphaere</hi> into two <hi>ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual</hi> parts, and is <hi>aequally</hi> diſtant from ech Pole of the worlde. And tooke his name of the <hi>aequator,</hi> either becauſe it is <hi>aequally</hi> in the middle of Heauen, as <hi>Euclide</hi> ſaith in his <hi>Opticks:</hi> or for that the Sunne, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to this Circle, maketh the day and night <hi>aequall.</hi> &amp; it is diuided in 360. <hi>aequall</hi> parts, which parts are called degrees. His Axe is the Axe of the world, and Poles, the Poles of the world.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Zodiack</hi> is a great Circle of the <hi>Sphaere,</hi> which croſſeth the <hi>Aequinoctiall</hi> in two points, the one being the head of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> the other of <hi>Libra,</hi> and ſwarneth from him in all other points, leaning toward ech Pole of the world in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> point of his greateſt ſwarning, 23. degrees, 30. minutes. This <hi>Zodiack</hi> is of breadth 12. degrees, and of length, that is to ſay, in compas 360. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and according to his length, is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided into 12. <hi>aequal</hi> parts, which are called the 12. ſignes. <hi>Aries, Taurus, Gemini, Cancer, Leo, Virgo, Libra, Scorpio, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gittarius, Capricornus, Aquarius</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:19308:8"/> 
                  <hi>Piſces.</hi> And ech ſigne contayneth of length 30. degrees. in the midle bredth of the <hi>Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diack,</hi> we imagine a Circle to paſſe, which we call the <hi>Ecliptick</hi> Circle or line: For that that when the Sunne and Moone bee both vnder this line in a <hi>Diameter:</hi> then the Moone is Eclipſed. Vnder this Circle the Sunne mooueth dayly (without decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning any waies) the quantity of one degree very neere in ech day. the reſt of the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets are found ſome times on one ſide the <hi>Ecliptick,</hi> &amp; ſome time on the other. This <hi>Zodiack</hi> taketh his name of a greeke word ſignifying a liuing creature: or as the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens will, is called <hi>Signifer,</hi> for that that it beareth the 12. Signes. the Axe of the <hi>Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diack</hi> and the <hi>Ecliptick,</hi> is all one, being a line diuers from the axe of the world, and the Poles bee two points alwayes ſo much diſtant from the Poles of the world: as the greateſt declination of the <hi>Ecliptick</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Colure</hi> doth generally ſignifie any Circle paſſing by the Poles of the worlde, and hath his name of his vnperfect ſhewing himſelfe in the motion of heauen. But now by the name of <hi>Colures,</hi> we vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d two
<pb facs="tcp:19308:8"/> great Circles, the one going fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Poles of the worlde by the points where the <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctiall</hi> and <hi>Zodiack</hi> cut them ſelues (which be called the <hi>Aequinoctiall</hi> points) and is called the <hi>Aequinoctiall Colure.</hi> The other paſſeth from the Poles of the worlde, by thoſe points of the <hi>Ecliptick</hi> which ſwarue moſt of all others from the <hi>Aequinoctiall</hi> line (which points are called the <hi>Solſticiall</hi> points) and this is called the <hi>Solſticial Colure.</hi> And here be you to know that theſe foure greater Circles which we haue defined: be ſtill the ſame through the whole worlde, and are ſayd to be moueable Circles: for ſo much as in the motion of heauen, they be alſo mooued. of which, ſome are moueable perfectly: as the <hi>Aequinocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all</hi> and <hi>Zodiack,</hi> (for they in the going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout of heauen, doe aſcend by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, till the whole Circle haue gone oure the <hi>Horiſon)</hi> ſome vnperfectly moueable, as the two <hi>Colures,</hi> which neuer ſhewe the whole Circle in any crooked <hi>Sphaere.</hi> the other two greater Circles which followe, be called fixed, for that they neuer mooue by the motion of heauen. But they be change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in euery Region.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19308:9"/>
               <p> The <hi>Horizon</hi> is a greater Circle diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the halfe of the Heauen which we ſee, from the halfe which we ſee not, and is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Latine <hi>Finitor,</hi> becauſe it endeth our ſight. The <hi>Horizon</hi> maketh fower princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal points, Eaſt, Weſt, North, and South. His Axe is a line imagined to fall from the point of heauen, which is directly ouer our head where we be, downe to the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d like a plumme line, and his Poles be the endes of that line, called the <hi>Verticall</hi> point, and point oppoſite to the <hi>Verticall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Meridian</hi> is alſo a great Circle, paſſing from the Poles of the world by our <hi>Verticall</hi> point, cutting the <hi>Horizon</hi> in the North and South points his Axe is a line going from the Eaſt point of the <hi>Horizon</hi> to the Weſt, and his Poles be the ſame points, and theſe two Circles doe alwayes chaunge, &amp; are diuers in euery Region: for ſo much as the <hi>Verticall</hi> point of euery Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is diuers, by the which the <hi>Meridian</hi> of neceſſitie muſt paſſe, and is the Pole al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the <hi>Horizon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:19308:9"/>
               <head>OF THE LESSER Circles of the Sphaere, and their names, and of their making.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He leſſe Circles of the <hi>Sphaere</hi> in number be fower. The Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picke of <hi>Cancer,</hi> the Tropicke of <hi>Capricorne,</hi> and the two Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes. The Tropicke of <hi>Cancer,</hi> is a leſſe Circle of the <hi>Sphaere,</hi> which is <hi>aequally</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from the <hi>Aequinoctial,</hi> lying betwixt the <hi>Aequinoctiall</hi> and the North Pole, and touching the <hi>Ecliptick</hi> in the beginning of <hi>Cancer.</hi> This Circle is deſcribed by the bodie of the Sunne in the longeſt day of Summer, at which time the Sunne is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the ſolſtitiall point, or beginning of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer.</hi> &amp; is called the Tropick, of a Greeke word, which ſignifieth a returning: becauſe the Sunne being brought to this point, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in his noone height, and returneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
               <p>The Tropicke of <hi>Capricorne,</hi> is a like Circle betwixt the <hi>Aequator</hi> &amp; the South pole, and is deſcribed by the Sunne in the ſhorteſt day of Winter, at which time the
<pb facs="tcp:19308:10"/> Sunne is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning of <hi>Capricorne,</hi> whereof it is called the Tropick of <hi>Capri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Articke Circle is a leſſe Circle of the <hi>Sphaere,</hi> deſcribed by the Northerne Pole of the <hi>Ecliptick. Proclus</hi> ſaith it is deſcribed by the formoſt foote of the great beare, and thereof taketh his name.</p>
               <p>The Antarticke is a like Circle deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by the South Pole of the <hi>Ecliptick,</hi> &amp; is called Antartick of the Greeke worde, which ſignifieth <hi>Oppoſition,</hi> becauſe it is oppoſite to the other.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Of the vſe of the Circles of the Sphaere or Globle.</head>
                  <p>THE moſt principall cauſe why Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers inuented the <hi>Aequinoctiall,</hi> was firſt, becauſe it is the meaſure of the firſt Heauen, by a conuenient, perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and <hi>aequal</hi> ſwiftneſſe. Secondly, it mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureth and limitteth the time of riſing of the Signes, as alſo the length of the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial daies, and times of the <hi>Aequinoctials,</hi> with declinations and right aſcentions of Starres, together with Longitudes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions.
<pb facs="tcp:19308:10"/> Laſtly, for the exection of the twelue howſen of Heauen. In like maner, the <hi>Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diack</hi> ſerueth for Latitudes &amp; Longitudes of Starres: for diſtinction of the times of the yeare: for the motions of all the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and effects of the ſame. Not vnlike be the vſes of the <hi>Colures</hi> and <hi>Meridian,</hi> ech ſhewing the greateſt declination of the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliptick:</hi> but eſpecially the <hi>Meridia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> which giueth as well al declinations of Starres, their noone height, and diſtinguiſheth the daies and nights into two; <hi>aequal</hi> parts, and ſerueth for the <hi>Horizon</hi> of the right <hi>Sphaere.</hi> It beginneth likewiſe and endeth all Longitudes of Regions, and ſheweth Latitudes and Eleuations of the Pole: It helpeth to diuide the 12. howſen. In like maner ſundrie and diuers be the vſes of the <hi>Horizon:</hi> As in ſeperating the hidden part of Heauen, from that which is ſeene, and ſheweth the place of riſing and ſetting of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Starre: how farre from Eaſt or Weſt, with his height. All which points are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected of Aſtronomers, as the <hi>Sphaere</hi> is ſecondarily diuided: that is to ſay, as he is a right, or a crooked Sphaere, which bee his properties and affections ment in the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb facs="tcp:19308:11"/> afore ſpecified. By a right <hi>Sphaere</hi> is ment ſuch a kinde of poſition of Heauen: as that neither Pole bee r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſed aboue ground, but that ech lye in the face of the earth. And ſuch a kinde of poſition haue they which dwell in <hi>Berſera,</hi> and the Iſlands of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucca,</hi> or ſuch like. Contrariwiſe, it is ſayd to bee a crooked <hi>Sphaere,</hi> when any one of the Poles is raiſed aboue ground. Such a <hi>Sphaere</hi> haue we at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and <hi>London:</hi> and generally all, which dwell not vnder the line. All which thinges for our better conceate, are ſhewed to the eye in the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Globe, whoſe names and diuiſions ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare at the firſt vewe: two things only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing waied. Firſt, that the mechanicall or materiall Globe which repreſenteth the firſt mooueable: beareth in him the fixed Starres, (not becauſe the Starres bee in the firſt mooueable) but becauſe their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſo litle in their own <hi>Sphaeres</hi> in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares, that they may ſeeme not to haue mooued at all in a mans his age from their places vnder which they be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt moue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: therefore they may bee ſuppoſed to ſtand in it. Secondly, the Globe repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Starres to vs in his connexitie,
<pb facs="tcp:19308:11"/> which appeare in Heauen in the concaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. For that our eye is not in the Globe but without. Furthermore in the Globe, beſides the aforenamed Circles, bee found three others of braſſe: the one being a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Circle of a litle quantitie, placed about the Pole which is eleuated: &amp; is called the hower Circle, whoſe ſtile is called the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex.</hi> An other is a thinne rule of braſſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting one quarter of a whole Circle, called the quadrant of Altitude, and is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie to be fixed (when ye vſe the Globe) on the middle of the halfe of your <hi>Meridian,</hi> which is aboue the <hi>Horizon:</hi> that is to ſay, 90. degrees aboue the <hi>Horizon.</hi> The third and laſt is a great halfe Circle lying at the <hi>Horizon,</hi> ſeruing aſwell for the erection of the ſcheme of Heauen, as any Circle of poſition. All which things being aduiſedly conſidered of, ye may proceede in the vſe of the Globe: As followeth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:19308:12"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <hi>HOW THE Globe is to be placed, readie for his vſe and practiſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe placing of the Globe ought to be ſuch, that the <hi>Horizon</hi> of the Globe may ſtand parallele or leuied to the true <hi>Horizon:</hi> and the <hi>Meridian</hi> of the Globe ſtand in the <hi>Superficies</hi> of the true <hi>Meridian</hi> of Heauen, and the Poles of the Globe and his Axe, anſwere exactly to the Poles and Axe of Heauen. Now to the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uying of the <hi>Horizon:</hi> there ought to bee at your Globe a hanging plummet. and for the <hi>Meridian,</hi> a Needle touched of the lode ſtone, and touching the rectifying of the Poles and Axe of the Globe, the <hi>eleuation</hi> of the Pole of heauen is firſt to be knowen. the meanes to performe and accompliſh the ſame, being ſuch as followe.</p>
               <div n="1" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 1. <hi>To finde a Meridian line in any place appoynted.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SEt vp on your <hi>Horizon</hi> or ſome plaine leuied boarde, a <hi>Gnomon</hi> of any reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb facs="tcp:19308:12"/> length then, (at ſuch time as the ſame ſhineth, deſcribe from the top of your <hi>Gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> a Circle by the tippe of his ſhadowe. and make a marke in the Circle where the ſhadowe ended, at your obſeruation (which muſt be before noone.) Then marke in the afternoone at what time the ende of the ſhadowe returneth into the ſame Circle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and make a marke at his point of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ſo ſhall ye haue a portion of the ſayde Circle incloſed betwixt the two points: If then ye diuide this portion into two <hi>aequal</hi> parts, and drawe a line from this middle point, by the point in which the <hi>Gnomon</hi> ſtandeth, it ſhalbe a <hi>Meridian</hi> line.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 2. <hi>To take the height of any Starre.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FRrom the point of Heauen, which is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly ouer our heads (being called the <hi>Verticall</hi> point, or <hi>Zenith:)</hi> are imagined diuers Circles to fall by euery degree and minute of the <hi>Horizon:</hi> all which Circles are called <hi>Verticals,</hi> &amp; ſerue for the height of Starres, for ſo much as the altitude of
<pb facs="tcp:19308:13"/> Sunne or ſtarre is the portion of the <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticall</hi> Circle, incloſed betwixt the <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of the Sunne or Starre (in the time of his obſeruation) and the <hi>Horizon,</hi> which height is thus found.</p>
                  <p>Take your <hi>Aſtrolabe,</hi> and let him hang freely by his ring, then turne vp his <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptral</hi> ſo long, that ye ſee the Starre (whoſe height yee ſeeke) thorowe his ſights: for then, howe many degrees and minutes are incloſed betwixt the <hi>Dioptrall</hi> and the line of your <hi>Aſtrolabe,</hi> which is parallele to the <hi>Horizon:</hi> ſo many hath that Starrs of height. as the ſeauenth day of <hi>Ianuarie. Anno.</hi> 1585. vnder the <hi>Meridian</hi> of Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, at 9. of the clocke I ſought the height of the Sunne. taking then my <hi>Aſtrolabe,</hi> and hanging him towarde the Sunne, and raiſing his <hi>Dioptrall</hi> till I eſpyed the Sunne. I found betwixt the <hi>Dioptral</hi> and the line repreſenting the <hi>Horizon</hi> ſeauen degrees, and 16. minutes, ſo much was the height of the Sunne at that time.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="proposition">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19308:13"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 3. <hi>To take the altitude of the Pole in in any place or countrey.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe altitude of the pole is the portion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>Meridia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> Circle incloſed betwixt the Pole and the <hi>Horizon.</hi> and is thus found. Find a <hi>Meridian</hi> line, and drawe him in the <hi>Horizon</hi> by the firſt propoſition: then take the height of any fixed Starre which ſetteth not (and that at the fore part of the night) at ſuch time as he is pointed vppon your <hi>Meridian</hi> line, by the ſecond propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Again the next morning, or any other morning take the height of the ſame ſtarre at ſuch time as hee is pointed with your <hi>Meridian</hi> line: then ſubduct the leſſe alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude from the greater, and diuide the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence into two <hi>aequall</hi> partes. Laſtly, adde halfe the difference to the leſſe altitude, ſo the whole number made giueth the altitude of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pole. As at Oxford I tooke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> height of a ſtarre in the fore part of a night in win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, being the tenth of December. 1584. at what time he was pointed with my <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian,</hi> and found his height. 55. degrees. 59. minutes. Againe the next morning I
<pb facs="tcp:19308:14"/> tooke his height, and found it 47. degrees 41. minutes. This leſſe altitude I ſubourted from the greater 55. degrees. 59. mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes, and the difference was 8. degrees. 18. minutes, which being parted, had 4. for his halfe, and 9. minutes. This halfe added to 47. degrees. 41. min. (the leſſe altitude) giueth 51. degrees. 50. minut. for the true eleuation of the Pole at Oxford.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 4. <hi>To rectifie the Globe perfectly for to be vſed.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>KNow firſt the eleuation of the Pole of Heauen, for the place where yee vſe the Globe, by the third propoſition, then erect the Pole of the Globe ſo many degrees a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue his <hi>Horizon,</hi> as the Pole of heauen is eleuated. Againe leuell the <hi>Horizon</hi> of your Globe by his hanging plummet, laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly turne his <hi>Meridian</hi> to the South by helpe of his Needle, and put his Quadrant of altitude vppon the 90. degree from his <hi>Horizon:</hi> for then the <hi>Meridian</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to the <hi>Meridian</hi> of heauen. Axe to axe, and Pole to Pole as is required. But this
<pb facs="tcp:19308:14"/> way of ſetting him South, albeit it be of antiquitie: yet hath it imperfection by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the variatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the needle. but of that ye ſhall heare more hereafter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 5. <hi>To finde the place of the Sunne at any tyme.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BY this place, is vnderſtoode the degree of the Ecliptick line, in which he is, and this place is thus found. In the <hi>Horizon</hi> of your Globe be ſet, the windes, the ſignes, and moneths with their daies. find therfore the day of your moneth in which ye would haue the place of the Sunne in the <hi>Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon</hi> of the globe. For looke what ſigne and degree of ſigne is right againſt the day, the ſame is the place of the Sunne. As on the twelfth day of December: <hi>Anno.</hi> 1584. I ſought the place of the Sunne. this day being had in the <hi>Horizon,</hi> I found the firſt degree of <hi>Capricorne,</hi> 32. minutes to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſware againſt it, and therefore that was then the place of the Sunne.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="proposition">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19308:15"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 6. <hi>To finde the declination of any point of the Ecliptick or of the Sunne, at any tyme.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe declination of any point of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliptick, Sunne, or any Starre, is the portion of the <hi>Meridian</hi> Circle, inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed betwixt the <hi>Aequinoctiall</hi> and the ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> point, Sunne, or ſtarre, and is found thus. Turne the poynt whoſe Declination yet ſeeke, to the <hi>Meridian</hi> of the Globe, and there ſee how many degrees and minutes there be of your <hi>Meridian</hi> incloſed betwixt the ſayd poynt and the <hi>Aequinoctiall.</hi> For ſo much is the Declination. ſo hath the Sunne in the 5. of <hi>Aries</hi> 2. degrees decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. And the 7. of <hi>Taurus</hi> 13. degrees. 52. minutes. and this declination is called Northren, when the point is of the North ſide the <hi>Aequinoctiall,</hi> and Southerne if of the South ſide. Here muſt ye alſo know, that two points of the Ecliptick want de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, and are the two <hi>Aequinoctials.</hi> Two haue greater declination then any<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and be the two <hi>Solſtitials.</hi> of the rest foure haue like declination.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="proposition">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19308:15"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 7. <hi>To finde the right aſcention of the Sunne, or any point of the Ecliptick line.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE right aſcention of any Starre, Sunne, or any point of the <hi>Ecliptick,</hi> is the portion of the <hi>Aequinoctiall</hi> Circle from the head of <hi>Aries,</hi> (where the <hi>Aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctiall</hi> taketh his beginning) and that point or degree of the ſame, which meeteth with the ſaid Starre, Sunne, or <hi>Ecliptick</hi> point, vnder the <hi>Meridian</hi> Circle in a croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Sphaere:</hi> being numbred orderly in the <hi>Aequinoctiall,</hi> and is thus found. turne the Starre, Sunne, or any point whoſe aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ye looke, vnder the <hi>Meridian</hi> of the Globe, and ſee then what portion of the <hi>ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quator</hi> is from the head of <hi>Aries</hi> to that point of the <hi>aequator</hi> which ſtandeth then vnder the <hi>Meridian:</hi> for the ſame portion, is the right aſcention of the Starre, Sun, or point looked for. So do I finde the right aſcention of <hi>Bootes</hi> a Starre, to be 209. degrees. 1. minut. And the right aſcention of the Sunne whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is in the firſt of <hi>Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> to be 27. degrees. 54. minuts. And the
<pb facs="tcp:19308:16"/> right aſcention of the firſt of <hi>Sagitarie,</hi> to be 237. degrees. 48. minuts.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 8. <hi>To finde the crooked aſcention of the Sunne, Starre, or any point of the Ecliptick.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE crooked aſcention of the Sunne, is that Ark of the <hi>aequator</hi> which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed betwixt the beginning of the <hi>aequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> and the point of the ſame which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vp with the Sunne in a crooked <hi>Sphaere,</hi> &amp; is found thus. Take the Sunne Starre, or point, whoſe crooked aſcention ye deſire: and put him to the Eaſt ſide of the <hi>Horizon</hi> till it touch: Then marke what part of the <hi>aequator</hi> is incloſed betwixt the beginning of it, and the point now in the <hi>Horizon,</hi> for ſo much is the crooked aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sunne, Starre, or point. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> doe I finde the crooked aſcention of the Sunne in the firſt of <hi>Taurus,</hi> to be the 12. degrees. 48. minuts. All this being in the Eleuation 52. degree. 0. minut.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="proposition">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19308:16"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 9. <hi>To find the difference of aſcention, or increaſe of the day.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE Sunne being in one and the ſelfe ſame point of the <hi>Ecliptick</hi> (except in the <hi>Aequinoctiall</hi> interſections) hath one degree of the <hi>aequator</hi> that commeth vp with him aboue the <hi>Horizon</hi> in any croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Sphaere,</hi> and an other, (not the ſame) that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vp with him in a right <hi>Sphaere.</hi> And therefore the portion of the <hi>aequator,</hi> betwixt the point of the ſaid, that commeth vp with the Sunne in the right <hi>Sphaere:</hi> and the point riſing with the ſame in the crooked <hi>Sphaere,</hi> is called the difference of aſcention. As in a right <hi>Sphaere</hi> the Sunne beeing in the firſt of <hi>Taurus,</hi> there riſeth with him, the 27. degree. 54. minut of the <hi>Aequinoctiall.</hi> (Which point alſo meeteth him vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>Meridia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> in a crooked <hi>Sphaere:</hi> for that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>Meridia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> of any crooked <hi>Sphaere,</hi> ſheweth the ſame that the <hi>Horizon</hi> doth in the right <hi>Sphaere.)</hi> but in the crooked <hi>Sphaere,</hi> where the Pole is eleuated 52. degrees, there riſeth with the Sunne the ſame daye, the 12. degree. 48. minut of the
<pb facs="tcp:19308:17"/> 
                     <hi>aequator.</hi> Subducting now the leſſe from the greater, the difference is 15. degrees. 6. minuts, and is called the difference of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention. And becauſe the Artificiall day of the crooked <hi>Sphaere,</hi> is longer or ſhorter then the <hi>Aequinoctiall</hi> day by twiſe this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference: therefore the difference of aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is called alſo the increaſe of the day. And this difference is thus found. Find the right aſcention of the Sunne by the 7. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: and againe finde his crooked aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention by the 9. propoſition: then ſubduce the leſſe from the greater, for the remaines is the difference of aſcention.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 10. <hi>To finde the length of the Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall day in any Region or Countrie.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FInde out the difference of aſcention of the place of the Sunne by the 9. propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and dubble the ſame then conuert is all into howers and parts of howers, allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing for one hower 15. degrees, and for a halfe 7. degrees. 30. minuts, &amp;c. This time which commeth of the difference of aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:19308:17"/> adde to 12. howers (if the place of the Sunne bee any degree betwixt <hi>Aries</hi> and <hi>Libra:</hi> or ſubduct it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 12. if he be betwixt <hi>Libra</hi> and <hi>Aries,)</hi> for the number made or left, is the length of the day. As the Sunne being in the firſt of <hi>Tanrus,</hi> his difference of aſcention is 15. degrees. 6. minuts: this dubble and conuerted into time, maketh 2. howers and 12. <hi>Aequinoctial</hi> minuts. And becauſe <hi>Tanrus</hi> is a Northerne Signe, ye muſt ad this difference to 12. howers, ſo do ye make 14. howers and 12. <hi>Aequinoctiall</hi> minuts, for the length of that whole day.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 11. <hi>To finde the hower of the Sunne riſing, or of his ſetting.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>KNowe the length of the Artificiall day by the 10. propoſition: and take halfe of the ſame day, for that ſheweth the hower of Sunne ſetting. But if ye recken ſo much from noone forward, it giueth Sunne riſe. As the Sunne being in the firſt of <hi>Taurus,</hi> the day is 14. howers and 12. minuts. The halfe is 7. howers and 6. minuts. I ſay then the Sunne ſetteth after 7. of the clocke, 6.
<pb facs="tcp:19308:18"/> minuts. Againe, thus much taken from noone forward, ſheweth the Sunne to riſe before 5. of the clocke, 6. minuts.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 12. <hi>An other way to finde the ſame more mechanically.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FInde the place of the Sunne by the 5. propoſition, and turne the ſaide place di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly vnder the <hi>Meridian:</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> put the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex of the hower Circle preciſely on 12. of the clocke. Laſtly, turne the ſaide place of the Sunne to the Eaſt ſide of the <hi>Horizo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> for when he is there, then ſhall the Index ſhewe the time of the Sunne riſing. And contrariwiſe, putting the place of the Sun to the Weſt, it ſheweth his ſetting.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 13. <hi>To finde how farre the Sunne riſeth or ſetteth from the true Eaſt or Weſt point any day.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FIrſt finde the place of the Sunne by the 5. propoſition: then turne the ſame place to the Eaſt ſide of the <hi>Horizon</hi> til he touch
<pb facs="tcp:19308:18"/> the ſame, for then the number of degrees in the <hi>Horizon,</hi> (incloſed betwixt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true Eaſt point and the place of the Sunne,) ſhewe how farr he riſeth and ſetteth from the true Eaſt: And this portion of the <hi>Horizon</hi> is called his bredth of riſing: and is called Northern bredth if the Sunne riſe beyond y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eaſt point toward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> North, &amp; Southern if contrary. Likewiſe are ye to knowe, that of the <hi>Ecliptick</hi> two points <hi>Aries</hi> and <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra</hi> haue no bredth of riſing. Two points alſo as <hi>Cancer</hi> and <hi>Capricorn</hi> haue grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then any other: and of the reſt fower points haue the like.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 14. <hi>To rectifie the Index of the hower Circle euery day as he ought.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FInde the place of the Sunne euery day in which ye vſe the Index, by the 5. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and put the ſaid place vnder the <hi>Meridian:</hi> this being done, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> put the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex on 12. of the clocke, for afterward in the motion of the Globe he will goe true as he ought.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="proposition">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19308:19"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 15. <hi>To finde the noone height of the Sunne for any day to come, or gone in any place whoſe eleuation is knowen.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe height of the Sunne, is the portion of the verticall Circle incloſed betwixt the Center of the Sunne and the <hi>Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon.</hi> But for as much as at noone the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian,</hi> and the <hi>Verticall</hi> of the Sunne bee all one Circle: therefore his noone height is the portion of the <hi>Meridian</hi> betwixt the Center of the Sunne and the <hi>Horizon.</hi> this height is thus to be knowen. Find the place of the Sunne for the day propoſed, and turne the ſame place vnder the <hi>Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian,</hi> for then the portion of the <hi>Meridian</hi> betwixt the ſayd place and the <hi>Horizon</hi> is his noone height. Thus found I the height of the Sunne at noone in Oxford, whoſe Pole is rayſed 51. degrees. 50. min. on the 2. day of May to be 59. degrees. 47. mi. and on the twelfth of Iune, to be 61. degrees. 41. minuts.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="proposition">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19308:19"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 16. <hi>To find the depreſsion of the Sunne at midnight.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AS the <hi>Meridian</hi> altitude is the portion of the <hi>Meridian</hi> from the Center of him, to the <hi>Horizon</hi> when hee is aboue the earth: ſo is his depreſſion the part of the <hi>Meridian</hi> betwixt the Center and the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon</hi> when he is vnder ground, and may thus bee knowen. Finde the place of the Sunne, and put it to the <hi>Meridian</hi> vnder the <hi>Horizon:</hi> for then the portion of the <hi>Meridian</hi> betwixt it &amp; the <hi>Horizon,</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his depreſſion. So find I the depreſſion of the Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, at Oxford (his place being the firſt of <hi>Taurus)</hi> to be 27. degrees. 40. min. but his place being the firſt of <hi>Scorpius,</hi> to be 50. degrees. 0. min.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 17. <hi>To find what height the Sunne ſhall haue at any certaine hower of any artificiall day.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TAke the place of the ſunne by the 5. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: &amp; rectifie the Index by the 14. pro. then turne the Globe, till the Index of
<pb facs="tcp:19308:20"/> the hower circle be on the hower, for whom ye deſire the height of the Sunne, and ſcop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Globe there, put the quadrant of altitude to the place of the Sunne, for his portion betwixt the place of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Sunne &amp; the <hi>Horizon,</hi> geueth his height. So find I the height of the Sunne at Oxford, at 9. of the clocke the 7. day of March. to be 24. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drees. 25. min. and at one of the clocke the ſame day, to be 34. degrees. 51. min.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 18. <hi>By any height of the Sunne geuen and his place: to find the hower of the day.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>LEt it bee, that either ye take the height of the Sunne at ſome time of the day by the ſecond propoſition: or that yee haue ſome height of him giuen by ſuppoſition, and ye would knowe by it what it is of the clocke that day at that time. Finde there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the place of the Sunne for that day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by the 5. propoſition &amp; rectifie the Index by the 14. propoſition. Laſtly put the place of the Sunne to the Quadrant of Altitude, and mooue them both vp and downe, till ye
<pb facs="tcp:19308:20"/> allowe him the ſame height in your Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant, as ye found or ſuppoſed him in trueth to haue. For then the Index of the hower Circle ſheweth what was or is of the clock, as finding the height of the Sunne before Noone on the ſeauenth of March, at Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, to be twentie fower degrees. 25. min. I founde it to haue beene then nine of the clocke.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 19. <hi>By the hower knowen, and the height of the Sunne at that hower: together with the Index, rectified as he ought: to find the place of the Sunne at that tyme.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>MOoue your Globe till his Index ſtand on the hower which was knowen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Then fixe the Globe for remoouing: Laſtly turne your Quadrant of altitude to the Ecliptick line, and looke what degree of the Ecliptick agreeth in your Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant with the height that was before kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, and that is the place of the Sunne on that day.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="proposition">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19308:21"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 20. <hi>The hower and place of the Sunne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing giuen: to find howe farre the Sunne is gone from the true Eaſt poynt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe place of the Sunne being giuen by ſuppoſition: rectifie the Index by the 14. propoſition: then turne the Globe till the Index ſhew the hower giuen. This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done, fixe the Globe that he mooue not away, and ſet the edge of the Quadrant of altitude to the place of the Sunne: and withall marke howe many degrees of the <hi>Horizo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> are incloſed betwixt the true Eaſt point, and the edge of the Quadrant, at ſuch time as he ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth on the place of the ſunne: for ſo much is hee diſtaunt in the <hi>Horizon</hi> from true Eaſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 21. <hi>The diſtance of the Sunne being geuen, from true Eaſt, together with his height at the ſame time, and the height of the Pole for the ſame region: to finde the true place of the Sunne, at any time.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TO the ende wee make not vnneceſſarie repetitions of the firſt principles: know
<pb facs="tcp:19308:21"/> this, that in all the propoſitions following, we alwayes ſuppoſe before the working, the Globe rightly rectifyed as is ſpecified in the beginning. For the performance therefore of this practiſe: firſt conſider dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently in what quarter of the yere ye be in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that is, whether it be betwixt the <hi>aequino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiall</hi> of March, and height of Summer: or betwixt height of Summer, and <hi>aequino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctial</hi> of September. Likewiſe whether be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>aequinoctial</hi> of September and dept of Winter: or betwixt dept of winter and <hi>aequinoctiall</hi> of March. For then ſet the edge of the quadrant of altitude at the true diſtance of the Sunne from the Eaſt: and turne the Globe till that quarter of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliptick come vnder him, which ſerueth for the quarter of the yeere in which ye be: and ſee what degree of that part of the Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick agreeth with the height propoſed: For that is the place of the Sunne at that time.</p>
                  <p>Note therefore here, that to the Spring (which is from the <hi>aequinoctiall</hi> of March till the height of Summer) anſwereth the part of the <hi>Zodiack</hi> from <hi>Aries</hi> to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer.</hi> To ſummer which is from the height till the <hi>aequinoctiall</hi> of September: anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb facs="tcp:19308:22"/> the part from <hi>Cancer</hi> to <hi>Libra.</hi> The <hi>Autume</hi> is guided by the quarter from <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra</hi> to <hi>Capricorne:</hi> and Winter by the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnes from <hi>Capricorne</hi> to <hi>Aries.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 22. <hi>The diſtance of the Sunne being geuen from true Eaſt, and the place of the ſame: to find the height of the Sunne which he hath at the ſame time.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>PLace the quadrant of altitude at the true diſtance from Eaſt, ſo ſhall hee cut the place of the Sunne by the 21. propoſition: and therefore the portion of the Quadrant betwixt the place of the Sunne, and the <hi>Horizon,</hi> is his height.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 23. <hi>The diſtance of the Sunne from true Eaſt being geuen, and his place: to find the hower of the day.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FIrſt hauing his place: rectifie your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex by the 14. propoſition: again ſetting the Quadrant of altitude in the diſtance
<pb facs="tcp:19308:22"/> from true Eaſt, reduce the place of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſunne, till he fall in the edge of the Quadrant, for then the Index doth ſhewe the hower.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 24. <hi>The diſtance of the Sunne being geuen from true Eaſt, and his height, to find the time of his riſing.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe diſtance being giuen, find his place by the 21 propoſition: and then rectifie the Index by the 14 propoſition: Laſtly put the place of the Sunne to the Eaſt ſide of the <hi>Horizon:</hi> for then the Index will ſhew the Sunne riſing.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 25. <hi>The diſtaunce of the Sunne being giuen from true Eaſt, and his height, to finde his Declination.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE diſtaunce being giuen, his place is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by the 21. propoſition: &amp; his place being knowne, giueth his Declination by the 6. propoſition: So may wee likewiſe by the ſaid diſtaunce (finding his place) finde his right or crooked aſcention, or difference
<pb facs="tcp:19308:23"/> of aſcentions, and length of Artificiall daies.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 26. <hi>The declination of the Sunne being knowne: to finde the place of the Sunne.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>COnſider firſt diligently in what quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the yeare ye be in, as was expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed before: then take that quarter of the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliptick</hi> which anſwereth to your quarter of the yeare: and mooue it ſtill vnder the <hi>Meridian</hi> of your Globe, till ye finde no more of the <hi>Meridian</hi> incloſed betwixt the <hi>aequator</hi> and <hi>Ecliptick,</hi> then the declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is giuen commeth vnto: for then looke what degree of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>Ecliptick</hi> is vnder the <hi>Meridian,</hi> that is the place of the Sun. As the declination of the Sunne in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the yeare betwixt the <hi>Aequinoctiall</hi> of March, and height of Summer was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to bee 11. degrees. 50. minuts. And to this quarter of the yeere, aunſwereth the quarter of the <hi>Ecliptick</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Aries</hi> to <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer.</hi> Therefore moouing the ſaid quarter vnder the <hi>Meridian,</hi> I found the firſt of
<pb facs="tcp:19308:23"/> 
                     <hi>Taurus</hi> to aunſwere to this declination: and therefore that was the place of the Sunne.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 27. <hi>The declination of the Sunne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing knowne: to finde the day of the Moneth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BY the declination giuen, finde the place of the Sunne by the 26. propoſition: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take the ſaid place in the <hi>Horizon</hi> of your Globe: for looke what day aunſwereth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, that is the day of the Moneth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 28. <hi>The day of the Moneth being knowne, to finde the length of the Plane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie hower.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE Artificiall day is from Sunne riſe to Sunne ſet: and the 12. part of this day, whether it be longer or ſhorter then an hower by the clocke, is the Planetarie ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer: and may thus be knowne. The day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en, finde the length of that day by the 10. propoſition: and diuide all by 12.
<pb facs="tcp:19308:24"/> The <hi>Quotient</hi> is the length of a Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netarie or Artificiall hower of that day. As the day being 15. howers by the clocke, I diuide it by 12. the <hi>Quotient</hi> is one ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and a quarter, and ſo much is a Plane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie hower of that day.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 29. <hi>The day of the Moneth being giuen: to finde the dawning of the day.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BY the day knowne, finde the place of the Sunne by the 5. propoſition: and then rectifie your Index by the 14. propoſition. Againe, take the degree of the <hi>Ecliptick</hi> which is oppoſite in a Diameter to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place of the Sunne: and mooue him toward the Weſt together with the Quadrant of Alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, till ye haue 18. degrees of height: for then the Index ſheweth the beginning of the dawning or ſpring of the day.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 30. <hi>To finde the length of the whole dawning.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FInde the beginning of the dawning by the 29. propoſition, and then the Sunne
<pb facs="tcp:19308:24"/> riſe by the 11. or 12. propoſition: for the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of thoſe times is the whole daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. And thus farre haue I followed ſuch concluſions, as haue a more orderly <hi>cohae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence:</hi> it remaineth now to ſhewe ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whoſe <hi>cohaerence</hi> is not ſo naturall.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 31. <hi>An other way to finde the length of the Artificiall day or night.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FInde the time of the Sunne riſing for your day propoſed by the 12. propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: then dubble all thoſe howers and partes of time which be from Sunne riſe till noone, for it giueth the Artificiall day. Or if ye nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber all the howers and parts from Sunne riſe to his ſetting, it giueth the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 32. <hi>To finde the hower of the day.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>PLace the Globe in the Sunne ſhine, and rectifie him to his vſe by the 4. propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then finde the place of the Sunne by the 5. propoſition. Againe, rectifie his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex
<pb facs="tcp:19308:25"/> by the 14. propoſition. Laſtly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the needle or pinne directly vp in the place of the Sunne: then turne the Globe vp till the pinne caſt no ſhadowe, for then the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex ſheweth what is then of the clocke.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 33. <hi>To finde the eleuation of the Pole, in any place.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>DRawe in the open ayre vpon ſome table that is leuell, a <hi>Meridian</hi> line by the 1. propoſition, and place the Globe ſo on it, that his <hi>Meridian</hi> Circle hang directly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it: then hauing the place of the Sunne, ſet a pinne right vp in it, and put the ſaid place and pinne cloſe to the <hi>Meridian</hi> cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. Laſtly, lift vp the Pole and <hi>Meridian</hi> Circle, till the pinne caſt no ſhadowe: for then the degrees betwixt the Pole and the <hi>Horizo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> be the true eleuatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that place. But this practiſe is to bee performed at noone onely or height of the day.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio</hi> 34. <hi>An other way to doe the ſame.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TAke the height of any fixed Starre (whom ye know) by the 2. propoſition,
<pb facs="tcp:19308:25"/> at ſuch time as he pointeth with the <hi>Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> line: then take the ſame Starre on the Globe, and by helpe of your Quadrant or <hi>Meridian</hi> Circle, cauſe him to haue the ſame Altitude in the Globe, and withall to be vnder the <hi>Meridian</hi> of the Globe: for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the Pole at his true Eleuation. So did I finde the Pole Starre (making my ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation at <hi>Oxford,</hi> the 11. of December 1584.) by the plaine <hi>Sphaere,</hi> to haue 55. degrees<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 59. minuts in Altitude, being the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the <hi>Meridian</hi> of Heauen: and when I ſet him at the ſame in my Globe, I found the Pole eleuated there 51. degrees. 50. mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts. And here ye are to knowe, that when ſoeuer ye haue by any way, the eleuation of the Pole in any place: if ye ſubduct the ſame eleuation from 90. degrees, it ſhall leaue and ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> the eleuation of the <hi>aequator</hi> in the ſayd place. So then the eleuation of the <hi>aequator</hi> at <hi>Oxford,</hi> is 38. degrees. 10. minuts.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 35. <hi>An other way of working the ſame, with more praeciſenes.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FIrſt learne by ſome good <hi>Ephemeris</hi> the preciſe place of the Sunne at noone
<pb facs="tcp:19308:26"/> in the day of your obſeruation: then againe learne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> exact declination of the ſaid place. Laſtly, with your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> take the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian</hi> height of the Sunne that day: And if the declination bee Northerne, then ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct it from the <hi>Meridian</hi> Altitude: but if it be Southerne, then ad it to the <hi>Meridian</hi> Altitude: ſo ſhall wee bring forth the Alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the <hi>aequator:</hi> and this Altitude be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubducted from 90. degrees, leaueth the Altitude of the Pole: but if the Sunne in the time of obſeruation be in the <hi>Aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctiall</hi> point, then is the <hi>Meridian</hi> Alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, the Altitude alſo of the <hi>aequator,</hi> and it ſubducted from 90. degrees, leaueth the Altitude of the Pole.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 36. <hi>To make a Horizontall Diall by the Globe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Horizontall</hi> Diall is ſuch a one as is made in a plaine <hi>Superficies,</hi> and lyeth leuell with the <hi>Horizon.</hi> For making whereof ye are to conſider, that from one Pole of the Globe to the other goe twelue great Circles, called hower Circles, and
<pb facs="tcp:19308:26"/> diuide the <hi>aequator</hi> into 24. <hi>aequall</hi> parts: And two of theſe bee two <hi>Colures.</hi> Put therefore the <hi>Solſtitiall Colure</hi> preciſely vnder the <hi>Meridian</hi> of your Globe, (the Globe being firſt perfectly rectified) and fixe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Globe ſo that he cannot mooue. Now marke how many degrees of the <hi>Horizon</hi> are incloſed betwixt the <hi>Meridian</hi> and the next hower Circle toward the Eaſt (which for diſtinction ſake I call the ſecond hower Circle) ſo likewiſe betwixt the firſt &amp; third, the firſt &amp; fourth, the firſt and fifth, the firſt and ſixt, the firſt and ſeuenth: (which is he that cutteth in the true Eaſt point) and ſet them all downe in tables: then drawe on ſome plaine thing a Circle, and diuide it into fower quarters, by drawing two croſſe lines: Now take the one ende of any of the two lines, and terme it the North point, ſo ſhall his other end be the South point, and the endes of the other line Eaſt and Weſt. Againe, diuide that quarter of this Circle which is betwixt the North point and Eaſt into 90. <hi>aequall</hi> parts, and let 90. ſtand at the Eaſt. So doe by the quarter betwixt North and Weſt. Laſtly, recken from the North point toward Eaſt, ſo many degrées
<pb facs="tcp:19308:27"/> as your tables ſhewe to haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> betwixt the firſt and ſecond hower line: and from the point where they ende, drawe a line by the Center of the ſaide Circle: and ſo doe by all the numbers of your tables: for ſo ſhall ye haue your hower lines drawne for a <hi>Horizontall</hi> Diall. In whoſe Center muſt be a ſtile exected, according to the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of your Pole. But this I leaue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, as meaning to ſet out an ample trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Dialling by it ſelfe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="37" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 37. <hi>How the Starres may be knowne by the Globe of Heauen.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>REctifie your Globe in the open ayre by the 4. propoſition, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take the height of any knowne Starre by your Inſtrument, afterward looke the ſame Starre on the Globe, and by helpe of your Quadrant of Altitude put the ſame Starre at his height taken before, and in the ſame Coaſt, &amp; then fixe the Globe. Now if ye would knowe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Starre of Heauen, then take the ſame Starre his height with your Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: laſtly, turne your Quadrant of Alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
<pb facs="tcp:19308:27"/> toward the ſame Coaſt of the Globe in which the Starre was in: &amp; looke what Starre ye finde in that Coaſt, to haue that Altitude, the ſame is he whom ye ſeeke. The like is to be done by all others.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 38. <hi>To finde the Longitude of any fixed Starre.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE Longitude of a Starre, is the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Ecliptick</hi> line, taken from the head of <hi>Aries,</hi> (according to the order of the Signes) to the point of the <hi>Ecliptick,</hi> cut by a Circle which paſſeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Pole of the <hi>Ecliptick,</hi> by the Center of the ſayd Starre: and is thus found. Take the Globe from his <hi>Horizon,</hi> and take of his <hi>Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> Circle, and fixe the ſame Circle by ſome meanes on the Poles of the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> then turne the Starre whoſe Longitude ye ſeeke, vnder the Circle: and recken all the Signes and parts from the head of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> to that point of the <hi>Ecliptick</hi> which is vnder the Circle with the Starre: for ſo much is his Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gitude. And the ſame point of the <hi>Ecliptick</hi> which is ſo vnder the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, ſhalbe called the place of that Starre. And the Starre is ſayd to bee vnder that
<pb facs="tcp:19308:28"/> Signe, of whom the aforeſaid point is a part. The Longitude may alſo be taken, if ye doe but fixe the Quadrant of Altitude in the Pole of the <hi>Ecliptick,</hi> and ſtirre not at all the <hi>Meridian</hi> Circle.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 39. <hi>To finde the Latitude of any Starre.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE Latitude of a Starre, is the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Circle that paſſeth from the Poles of the <hi>Ecliptick</hi> line, by the Center of any Starre, which is incloſed betwixt the <hi>Ecliptick</hi> line and the Center of the Starre, and is found thus. Your Circle ſtanding in the Poles of the <hi>Zodiack</hi> as before: turne the Starr vnder the ſaid Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle: for then the portion of that Circle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Starre and the <hi>Ecliptick,</hi> is his Latitude. And this Latitude is Northern, when the Starre is North from the <hi>Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick:</hi> and Southerne of contrary.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="40" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 40. <hi>To finde what Starres be aboue ground at any time of the day or night.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IF ye would know it in the day time whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Sunne ſhineth, then take the height of the Sunne by the 2. propoſition: after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb facs="tcp:19308:28"/> finde his place by the 5. propoſition: laſtly, by help of the Quadrant of Altitude, ſet the Sunne at his owne height &amp; Coaſt, and then all the Starres aboue the <hi>Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon</hi> doe appeare in the Globe. Now if it be in the night, and the Starres appeare, then take the height of ſome knowne Starre, and place the ſame Starr at his due height in the Globe, ſo ſhall ye ſee the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="41" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 41. <hi>To doe the ſame without Sunne, or appearaunce of any Starre.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>YE muſt knowe what it is of the clocke at that time when ye would worke this concluſion: then rectifie the Index by the 14. propoſition: Laſtly, turne the Globe till the Index come on the ſame hower as is giuen by the clocke, for then the Starres appeare as they ſhould.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="42" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 42. <hi>To finde what Starres will paſſe directly ouer our heads in the motion of the heauen.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AFter that the Quadrant of Altitudes is fixed in his due place, as is ſpoken of before, ſo that he now doe ſhewe the <hi>Zenith</hi> or <hi>Verticall</hi> point: then mooue about the
<pb facs="tcp:19308:29"/> Globe, and marke what Starres paſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Zenith</hi> in this motion, for thoſe bee ſuch as goe by our heads, &amp; are called ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Culminant</hi> ſtarres, ſometimes <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall</hi> ſtarres, and haue their cheefeſt vſe in Aſtrologie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="43" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 43. <hi>To knowe with what degree of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliptick any Starre riſed, commeth to the Meridian: or ſetteth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>MOue the Globe till the Starre whom ye propoſe, aſcend aboue the <hi>Horizon,</hi> and then marke the degrée of the <hi>Ecliptick</hi> that riſeth with him. Againe mooue him to the <hi>Meridian,</hi> and marke the degree of the <hi>Ecliptick,</hi> ſo doe by him in the Weſt ſide of the <hi>Horizon,</hi> and ye ſhal haue your intent.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="44" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 44. <hi>To knowe the hower of any Starres riſing.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>REctifie the Index by the 14. propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then turne the Globe til the ſaid Starre (whoſe time of riſing ye deſire,) touch the Eaſt ſide of the <hi>Horizon:</hi> for then the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex giueth his time of riſing. And if ye turne him to the <hi>Meridian,</hi> the Index will ſhewe his time of comming the ther: or if ye
<pb facs="tcp:19308:29"/> turne him to the Weſt ſide of the <hi>Horizo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> the Index ſheweth his ſetting.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="45" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 45. <hi>To find in how long time any whole ſigne ariſeth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>REctifie the <hi>Index</hi> by the fowerteenth propoſition: then put the beginning of the ſigne (whoſe time of riſing ye ſeeke) to the Eaſt part of the <hi>Horizon:</hi> and marke what the <hi>Index</hi> ſtandeth on then: againe, put the laſt degree of the ſayde ſigne to the <hi>Horizon,</hi> and ſee what the Index ſheweth: for the differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the two times by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex, is the time in which that ſigne riſeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="46" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 46. <hi>To find in what coaſt any ſtarre is, and how many degrees from the Meridian.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FInde the Starres aboue ground by the 40. propoſition: then the Globe beeing fixed: put the Quadrant of altitude to any State. Then ſhall the foote of the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant ſhewe in the <hi>Horizon,</hi> how farre the ſame Starre is from Eaſt, Weſt, North or South. But if ye firſt rectifie your Index by the 14. propoſition: and then finde the ſtarres aboue by the 40. propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Agayn
<pb facs="tcp:19308:30"/> at the ſame time marke where the Index ſtandeth: laſtly put any Starre vnder the Meridian, and againe note the ſtanding of the Index: the differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of thoſe two times ſhewed by the Index, is the diſtance of that ſtarre from the <hi>Meridian,</hi> in the time of your obſeruation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="47" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 47. <hi>To find what Starres riſe or ſet any day, Coſmically, Achronically or Helically.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SVch ſtarres as bee neare to the ſunne in any day, and aſcende aboue the <hi>Horizon</hi> a little before the appearance of the ſame: are ſaid to ryſe helically, and ſuch Starres as ſet very little after the Sunne, are ſayd to ſet helically. Againe ſuch Starres as aſcend together with the Sunne, and ſuch as ſet at the ſame time, are ſayd to riſe and ſet coſmically. Laſtly, ſuch ſtarres as ſet together with the Sunne: and ſuch as riſe at the ſame time: are ſayde to ſet and riſe achronically, and ſuch may bee thus found. Rectifie the Index by the 14. propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition: and turne the place of the Sunne to the Eaſt ſide of the <hi>Horizon:</hi> for the ſtarres going immediatly before the Sunne, riſe
<pb facs="tcp:19308:30"/> helically. and thoſe in the <hi>Horizon</hi> riſe coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mically: and they that are in the <hi>Horizon</hi> in the weſt, doe ſet coſmically, and ſuch as immediatly riſe after the Sunne, doe ſette helically. Laſtly turne the Sunne to the Weſt point of the <hi>Horizon,</hi> and looke what ſtarres touch the <hi>Horizon</hi> with him, ſuch ſet achronically: and ſuch as are at the ſame time riſing in the Eaſt, riſe Achroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="48" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 48. <hi>To knowe the hower of the night, at any time by the Starres.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>REctifie the Index by the 14. propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then againe finde what ſtarres bee aboue ground at the ſame time, when yee would know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hower, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 40. propoſition: for then the Index will ſhewe the hower.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="49" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 49 <hi>To find the fower Cardinall points of heauen at any time of day or night.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe fower Cardinall points, bee the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer degrees of the Ecliptick, where of one is in the Eaſt riſing: an other is in the South or vnder the <hi>Meridian,</hi> aboue at the ſame time: the third in the Weſt ſetting,
<pb facs="tcp:19308:31"/> and the fourth vnder the <hi>Meridian</hi> beneath ground, all at one inſtant, in the time of any geniture, or motion of any queſtion, and are thus knowen. If yee ſeeke them in the day (the Sunne ſhining) then find the ſtarres aboue ground by the 40. propoſition: and with all marke the degree of the Ecliptick in the Eaſt. ſo likewiſe in the South, Weſt and North, for thoſe be then the Cardinall points. Againe, if it be in the night, then find the ſtarres aboue by the ſame 40. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. and the pointes ſhall likewiſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. Laſtly, if nether the Sunne ſhine, or ſtarre: then knowe the hower by the clock, and afterward find the ſtarres aboue grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d at the ſayd hower by the 41. propoſition. ſo ſhall the pointes be geuen as before.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="50" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 50. <hi>To find the bignes of the angle, made betwixt the Meridian Circle, and any Circle of poſition.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>CIrcles of Poſition bee all ſuch, as are drawen from the North point of any <hi>Horizon</hi> by the Center of any ſtarre, and ſo to go to the South point of the ſame <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rizon,</hi> to returne to the North againe. And euery one of theſe Circles doth make ſome
<pb facs="tcp:19308:31"/> with the <hi>Meridian,</hi> and the ſayd angle hath his bignes ſhewed, by a portion of the fixed <hi>Verticall:</hi> ſo that to find the bignes of the angle made betwixt the <hi>Meridian</hi> and any Circle of poſition: is to find the portion of the fixed <hi>Vertical,</hi> incloſed betwixt the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian</hi> and the ſaid Circle of poſition. that portion is thus found. Put your quadrant of altitude, to the true Eaſt point, then raiſe vp your Braſſe halfe Circle as high aboue the <hi>Horizon</hi> as yee pleaſe: ſo that it may nowe repreſent ſome circle of poſition. for then the degrees of the Quadrant of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude from the <hi>Meridian</hi> to this circle: be the bignes of the angle made betwixt the <hi>Meridian,</hi> and the Circle of poſition. but if your circle of poſition fall on the Weſt ſide of the <hi>Meridian,</hi> then put the Quadrant to the Weſt point; and worke as before.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="51" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſitio.</hi> 51. <hi>To find the beginnings and endes of the</hi> 12 <hi>howſes of Heauen.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>COncerning the erecting the ſcheme of heauen, or as we commonly call it the twelue howſen: though fower diuers waies haue bene receaued, touching the howſen, how they ought to bee taken: yet it is not
<pb facs="tcp:19308:32"/> our entent to diſcourſe of that queſtion, but to ſhewe howe they ought to be erected, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the moſt vſuall way, ſet downe by <hi>Regiomontanus,</hi> &amp; called reaſonable. Wherefore firſt ye are to knowe, that in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Horizon</hi> whereſoeuer wee be, wee doe imagine ſixe circles to be drawen from the North point of the <hi>Horizon</hi> to the South of the ſame, and diuiding the <hi>Aequinoctiall</hi> into 12 <hi>aequall</hi> partes, and the 12. ſpaces betwixt theſe circles, are called the twelue howſes. (&amp; two of the 6. circles are alwaies the <hi>Meridian</hi> and <hi>Horizon.)</hi> in euery one of theſe howſen is incloſed ſome portion of the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> and one portion is greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an other. ſo that to erect the twelue how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, is to find out the portion of the Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick incloſed in ech ſpace, &amp; to do it, we thus proceede. Firſt find out the fower Cardinal points by the 49. propoſition, for thoſe be the beginnings of 4. howſen of the twelue: the Cardinall point vnder the <hi>Meridian</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue ground, is the beginning of the tenth howſe. This done, fixe the Globe, then rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the degree of the <hi>aequator</hi> (being then vnder the <hi>Meridian)</hi> 30. degrees to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Eaſt point, &amp; raiſe vp your braſſe
<pb facs="tcp:19308:32"/> halfe circle to ſtand on the point of the <hi>ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quator</hi> on which yee left. For looke then what degre of the Ecliptick is cut then by the braſſe halfe Circle: the ſame is the end of the tenth howſe, and beginning of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuenth. Againe, yet recken 30. degrees more in the <hi>aequator</hi> toward the Eaſt, and put the braſſe halfe circle to it, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take the degree cut in the Ecliptick, for that is the end of the eleuenth howſe, and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the twelfth. Againe the Cardinall point of the Eaſt, is the end of the twelfth howſe, and beginning of the firſt howſe. Now if in like ſort ye goe from the degree of the <hi>aequator</hi> vnder the <hi>Meridian,</hi> by ech 30. degree of the ſame toward the Weſt point, and ſtill obſerue the degres cut in the Ecliptick: yee ſhall haue the beginnings and ends of the ninth, eighth and ſeauenth howſe. Thus hauing erected ſixe howſen, the degrees of the <hi>Zodiack</hi> which are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to theſe in a Diameter, (one to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) bee the beginnings and ends of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſixe howſen, which were to be found. And here muſt yee note, that the firſt howſe beginneth at the Eaſt point, and goeth vnder the ground toward the <hi>Meridian</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19308:33"/> Circle, the ſecond and the third ſucceede. the fowerth, beginning at the <hi>Meridian</hi> vnder ground comming toward Weſt, the fifth and ſixth ſucceed, the ſeuenth begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in the Weſt, and goeth aboue ground toward the <hi>Meridian,</hi> the eight and ninth ſucceed. Other concluſions leſſe profitable I wittingly auoyded: and the more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, deferred to a more conuenient time.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <l>Pa: 3. li: 13. indicem, lege iudicem.</l>
            <l>Pa: 23. li: 1. ſame, lege Sunne.</l>
            <l>Pa: 24. li: 1. lege Ver.</l>
            <l>Pa: 46. li: 16. till ye, lege till it.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:19308:33"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
